# 🏦 Bank Transaction Analysis — SQL Portfolio Project

> **Skills demonstrated:** T-SQL · Window Functions · CTEs · Data Modeling · Fraud Detection · KPI Reporting
> **Tool:** SQL Server Management Studio (SSMS)
> **Industry:** Finance & Banking | 

---

## 📌 Project Overview

This project simulates a real-world bank database and uses T-SQL to answer key business questions about customer behavior, fraud detection, branch performance, and financial KPIs — the exact kind of work done by Data Analysts at banks and fintech companies.

---

## 🗂️ Database Schema

```
branches
   └── customers
          └── accounts
                 └── transactions
```

| Table | Rows | Description |
|---|---|---|
| `branches` | 10 | Bank branches across US cities |
| `customers` | 100 | Customer demographics |
| `accounts` | 175 | Checking, savings, and credit accounts |
| `transactions` | 8,911 | All transactions with fraud flags |

---

## 🔍 10 Business Queries

| # | Business Question | Key T-SQL Skills |
|---|---|---|
| 1 | Monthly cash flow — deposits vs withdrawals | `DATEADD`, `DATEDIFF`, `CASE WHEN`, `GROUP BY` |
| 2 | Top 5 customers by total spending | `TOP`, multi-table `JOIN`, aggregation |
| 3 | Fraud & suspicious transaction report | `DATEPART`, risk scoring with `CASE WHEN` |
| 4 | Running balance per account over time | `SUM() OVER`, `PARTITION BY`, window function |
| 5 | Spending breakdown by category per customer | Pivot-style `CASE WHEN` aggregation |
| 6 | Branch performance analysis | `LEFT JOIN`, multi-table aggregation |
| 7 | High-value customers with fraud alerts | CTEs, customer tier classification |
| 8 | Month-over-month transaction growth | `LAG()`, CTEs, percentage change |
| 9 | Customer spending rank within each city | `RANK() OVER PARTITION BY` |
| 10 | Executive KPI summary dashboard | Multi-CTE, full business summary |

---

## 💡 Key Insights Uncovered

- Over **1,100 flagged transactions** detected — late-night ATM withdrawals, unknown merchants, and cross-city large transfers are the top fraud signals
- **Travel and Online** categories account for the highest average transaction values
- **Northeast region** (New York) holds the most total assets under management across all branches
- Month-over-month analysis shows consistent transaction volume throughout 2024 with salary deposit spikes at month start
- Overall fraud rate sits at approximately **12–14%** of all transactions — above the industry average of 5%, signalling a need for tighter controls

---


## 🛠️ Tools Used

- **SQL Server Express** database engine
- **SSMS** — SQL Server Management Studio, query editor
- **GitHub** version control and portfolio hosting

---

## 👤 Author

**Sadgee Jain**
· [GitHub](https://github.com/yourusername) · yourname@email.com

---

*All data in this project is synthetically generated for portfolio purposes. No real customer information is used. *

